<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="appendixA">
  <title id="a_title">Licenses</title>

  <para>This appendix contains details for the following third-party
  licenses:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="ScaLAPACK">ScaLAPACK</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="bsdiff">bsdiff</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="JsonCpp">JsonCpp</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="MPICH2">MPICH2</link></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section id="Affero">
    <title>Affero GPL</title>

    <para>SciDB is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the Affero General Public License, version 3, as
    published by the Free Software Foundation.</para>

    <para>SciDB is distributed "AS-IS" AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
    INCLUDING ANY IMPLIED WARRANTY OF MERCHANTABILITY, NON-INFRINGEMENT, OR
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the Affero General Public License at
    <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.html">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.html</ulink>
    for the complete license terms.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ScaLAPACK">
    <title>ScaLAPACK</title>

    <para>Copyright (c) 1992-2011 The University of Tennessee and The
    University of Tennessee Research Foundation. All rights reserved.</para>

    <para>Copyright (c) 2000-2011 The University of California Berkeley. All
    rights reserved.</para>

    <para>Copyright (c) 2006-2011 The University of Colorado Denver. All
    rights reserved.</para>

    <para>The copyright holders provide no reassurances that the source code
    provided does not infringe any patent, copyright, or any other
    intellectual property rights of third parties. The copyright holders
    disclaim any liability to any recipient for claims brought against
    recipient by any third party for infringement of that parties intellectual
    property rights.</para>

    <para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
    "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
    TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
    PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR
    CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL,
    EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
    PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR
    PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
    NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
    SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="bsdiff">
    <title>bsdiff</title>

    <para><programlisting>Copyright 2003-2005 Colin Percival
All rights reserved

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted providing that the following conditions 
are met:
1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
   notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
   notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
   documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHOR ``AS IS'' AND ANY EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED
WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR ANY
DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS
OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT,
STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING
IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE
POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</programlisting></para>
  </section>

  <section id="JsonCpp">
    <title>JsonCpp</title>

    <programlisting>The JsonCpp library's source code, including accompanying documentation, 
tests and demonstration applications, are licensed under the following
conditions...

The author (Baptiste Lepilleur) explicitly disclaims copyright in all 
jurisdictions which recognize such a disclaimer. In such jurisdictions, 
this software is released into the Public Domain.

In jurisdictions which do not recognize Public Domain property (e.g. Germany as of
2010), this software is Copyright (c) 2007-2010 by Baptiste Lepilleur, and is
released under the terms of the MIT License (see below).

In jurisdictions which recognize Public Domain property, the user of this 
software may choose to accept it either as 1) Public Domain, 2) under the 
conditions of the MIT License (see below), or 3) under the terms of dual 
Public Domain/MIT License conditions described here, as they choose.

The MIT License is about as close to Public Domain as a license can get, and is
described in clear, concise terms at:

   http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIT_License
   
The full text of the MIT License follows:

========================================================================
Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Baptiste Lepilleur

Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation
files (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without
restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy,
modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies
of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be
included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS
BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN
ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN
CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
SOFTWARE.
========================================================================
(END LICENSE TEXT)

The MIT license is compatible with both the GPL and commercial
software, affording one all of the rights of Public Domain with the
minor nuisance of being required to keep the above copyright notice
and license text in the source code. Note also that by accepting the
Public Domain "license" you can re-license your copy using whatever
license you like.</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="MPICH2">
    <title>MPICH2</title>

    <para><programlisting>	                                  COPYRIGHT
	
	The following is a notice of limited availability of the code, and disclaimer
	which must be included in the prologue of the code and in all source listings
	of the code.
	
	Copyright Notice
	 + 2002 University of Chicago
	
	Permission is hereby granted to use, reproduce, prepare derivative works, and
	to redistribute to others.  This software was authored by:
	
	Argonne National Laboratory Group
	W. Gropp: (630) 252-4318; FAX: (630) 252-5986; e-mail: gropp@mcs.anl.gov
	E. Lusk:  (630) 252-7852; FAX: (630) 252-5986; e-mail: lusk@mcs.anl.gov
	Mathematics and Computer Science Division
	Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne IL 60439
	
	
	                              GOVERNMENT LICENSE
	
	Portions of this material resulted from work developed under a U.S.
	Government Contract and are subject to the following license: the Government
	is granted for itself and others acting on its behalf a paid-up, nonexclusive,
	irrevocable worldwide license in this computer software to reproduce, prepare
	derivative works, and perform publicly and display publicly.
	
	                                  DISCLAIMER
	
	This computer code material was prepared, in part, as an account of work
	sponsored by an agency of the United States Government.  Neither the United
	States, nor the University of Chicago, nor any of their employees, makes any
	warranty express or implied, or assumes any legal liability or responsibility
	for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus,
	product, or process disclosed, or represents that its use would not infringe
	privately owned rights.
	
	Portions of this code were written by Microsoft. Those portions are
	Copyright (c) 2007 Microsoft Corporation. Microsoft grants permission to
	use, reproduce, prepare derivative works, and to redistribute to
	others. The code is licensed "as is." The User bears the risk of using
	it. Microsoft gives no express warranties, guarantees or
	conditions. To the extent permitted by law, Microsoft excludes the
	implied warranties of merchantability, fitness for a particular
	purpose and non-infringement.</programlisting></para>
  </section>
</appendix>
