<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"docbookV4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "scidb_ug.ent">
<!ENTITY scidb_version "14.12">
<!ENTITY scidb_revision "7896">
<!ENTITY scidb_year "2014">
]>
<chapter id="installationChapter">
  <title>SciDB Installation and Administration</title>

  <para><indexterm>
      <primary>platforms</primary>
    </indexterm><indexterm>
      <primary>SciDB</primary>

      <secondary>platforms</secondary>
    </indexterm>SciDB is supported on the following platforms:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Ubuntu 12.04 or 14.04</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>CentOS 6</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux (RHEL) 6</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <note>
    <para>SciDB requires a 64-bit (x86_64 or amd64) platform.</para>
  </note>

  <para>A complete SciDB installation is a multi-database environment that
  includes the core SciDB engine, Postgres, the open source SQL database
  engine which is used for system catalog data, as well as ScaLAPACK/MPI which
  is used as a computational engine for dense linear algebra.</para>

  <note>
    <para>SciDB installation must be done by an account with root
    privileges.</para>
  </note>

  <para><indexterm>
      <primary>SciDB</primary>

      <secondary>contact</secondary>
    </indexterm><indexterm>
      <primary>support</primary>
    </indexterm>To report issues, contact
  <email>support@paradigm4.com</email>.</para>

  <section id="installationResources">
    <title>Installation Resources</title>

    <para>The linchpin of the SciDB installation procedure is the Cluster
    Install script, located at <ulink
    url="www.scidb.org/forum/viewforum.php?f=16">www.scidb.org/forum/viewforum.php?f=16</ulink>.
    In addition, these other resources are available:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configurator (generates a config.ini file from your
          interactive input): <ulink
          url="https://github.com/Paradigm4/configurator">https://github.com/Paradigm4/configurator</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A how-to video on installing SciDB is available here: <ulink
          url="http://www.paradigm4.com/scidb-installation-video/">http://www.paradigm4.com/scidb-installation-video/</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A backup-and-restore script, useful if you are upgrading from
          a previous version of SciDB. The script is available on your SciDB
          cluster (provided your existing installation is version 14.3 or
          later; previous versions did not include this script) in
          /opt/scidb/14.3/bin/scidb_backup.py or
          /opt/scidb/14.8/bin/scidb_backup.py.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>An appendix describing the detailed steps which are
          automatically performed by the Cluster Install script. If local
          policies prevent you from running the cluster install script, you
          can use this appendix as a guide to manual installation. See <xref
          linkend="troubleInstall"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>See the remainder of the chapter for more details about the
    installation process and files.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Previous versions (14.3 and 14.8) included a script to help you
      install without root privileges—on CentOS/RHEL only. However, we are not
      aware of anyone actively using that script, so in this release it is not
      supported. If you need such a script, contact us at
      support@paradigm4.com.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="firstTimeInstallation">
    <title>First-Time Installation</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>SciDB</primary>

      <secondary>installing for the first time</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>install SciDB</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>If you are installing SciDB for the first time on a cluster, the
    process is straightforward:</para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>Prepare the platform. This includes creating or adjusting user
        accounts and configuring storage for the SciDB database files. For
        details, see <xref linkend="PlatformPrep"/>.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Prepare a configuration file for SciDB. See <xref
        linkend="ConfiguringSciDB"/>. </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Run the cluster install script. See <xref
        linkend="runClusterInstall"/>.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <section xml:id="PlatformPrep">
      <title>Preparing the Platform</title>

      <para>Before installing SciDB, the following steps are required to
      prepare a cluster for running SciDB. Many of these steps must be
      executed as the Linux 'root' account.</para>

      <section xml:id="linuxAccounts">
        <title>Prepare Accounts</title>

        <para>Before you install SciDB, you need to ensure that you have a
        user account under which SciDB processes -- on all servers of the
        cluster -- will run. This will also be the owner of all data and log
        files created by SciDB, and it is the account that initializes,
        starts, and stops the SciDB cluster. This account must have
        passwordless SSH access configured between the default coordinator
        server and all other servers in the cluster. Throughout this
        documentation, this account is referred to as the scidb account,
        although strictly speaking, it can be any account with the appropriate
        settings.</para>

        <para>In addition to setting up the scidb account, you may need to
        perform these tasks depending on your operating system:<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Ubuntu does not enable root login by default. To enable
              root login on Ubuntu, run the following command:<programlisting>sudo passwd</programlisting>Sudo
              will prompt you for your password, and then ask you to supply a
              new password for root.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>For CentOS and RHEL, you should create a user account
              (<command>adduser</command>), and provide sudo access for this
              account. For details, see your OS documentation. If you need to
              install <command>sudo</command>, execute the following command
              (as root):<programlisting>yum install sudo</programlisting></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="DataDir">
        <title>Configure Storage</title>

        <note>
          <para>This action must be performed by a user with sudo privileges
          on each server in the cluster. Once created, the base path should be
          owned by the account used by SciDB.</para>
        </note>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>configuration</primary>
          </indexterm><indexterm>
            <primary>storage</primary>

            <secondary>configuring</secondary>
          </indexterm>On each server, create a directory on the local file
        system to serve as the data directory for each instance. This must be
        accessible via the same path name on every server.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="ConfiguringSciDB">
      <title>Configuring SciDB</title>

      <para>This section shows a configuration file: the result of using the
      configurator (<ulink
      url="https://github.com/Paradigm4/configurator">https://github.com/Paradigm4/configurator</ulink>)
      utility. The configurator will place the file wherever you choose. Then,
      the Cluster Install script will move the file to its proper location on
      the default coordinator server -- in
      <literal>/opt/scidb/&scidb_version;/etc/config.ini.</literal></para>

      <para>The configuration 'test1' below is an example of the configuration
      for a single-node, four-instance system:<programlisting>[test1]
server-0=localhost,3
db_user=test1user
db_passwd=test1passwd
install_root=/opt/scidb/&scidb_version;
metadata=/opt/scidb/&scidb_version;/share/scidb/meta.sql
pluginsdir=/opt/scidb/&scidb_version;/lib/scidb/plugins
logconf=/opt/scidb/&scidb_version;/share/scidb/log4cxx.properties
base-path=/home/scidb/data
base-port=1239
network-buffer=1024
mem-array-threshold=1024
smgr-cache-size=1024
execution-threads=16
result-prefetch-queue-size=4
result-prefetch-threads=4</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="runClusterInstall">
      <title>Running Cluster Install</title>

      <para>The Cluster Install script, and a README file with instructions
      for running it, are here: <ulink
    url="www.scidb.org/forum/viewforum.php?f=16">www.scidb.org/forum/viewforum.php?f=16</ulink>.
</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="StartingSciDB">
      <title>Starting SciDB</title>

      <para>You start SciDB from the server containing the default coordinator
      instance.</para>

      <para>As the scidb user, run the following command to start a SciDB
      database. The command starts the set of local SciDB instances specified
      in your config.ini file.</para>

      <note>
        <simpara>For the following command, replace
        <replaceable>scidb_cluster_name</replaceable> with the name of your
        actual cluster. (In the sample configuration of the preceding section,
        the value of <replaceable>scidb_cluster_name</replaceable> is
        'test1'.</simpara>

        <simpara>Also note that the cluster install script automatically
        performs the first two steps of this procedure.</simpara>
      </note>

      <programlisting>scidb.py startall <replaceable>scidb_cluster_name</replaceable></programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>Initialization may fail if you are using the Lustre file system.
        To correct the problem, use the <code>-o localflock</code> option when
        mounting the file system.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="upgradingSciDB">
    <title>Upgrading SciDB</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>SciDB</primary>

        <secondary>upgrading</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>upgrade SciDB</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>versions</primary>

        <secondary>SciDB</secondary>
      </indexterm>This section describes the process for installing SciDB
    14.12 on a cluster where a previous version of SciDB is already installed.
    This section uses the following conventions:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To represent your current version: <emphasis
          role="bold">scidbOldVersion</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To represent the new version that you are installing:
          <emphasis role="bold">scidbNewVersion</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>For example, if you are upgrading from 14.8 to 14.12:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">scidbOldVersion</emphasis> = 14.8</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">scidbNewVersion</emphasis> =
          14.12</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>If you are installing SciDB 14.12 on a cluster with a previous
    version of SciDB, perform the following steps:</para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Backup.</emphasis> If your existing
        installation is 14.3 or later, you should back up your data using the
        script, <code>scidb_backup.py</code>. This file is in the
        /opt/scidb/&lt;scidbOldVersion&gt;/bin folder. (If your existing
        installation is a version earlier than 14.3, you must perform manual
        backup.) First, confirm that you have enough storage space, because
        the following command will backup all your SciDB arrays. From the
        <emphasis role="bold">scidb</emphasis> user account, run the backup
        script. As an example, the following command creates a folder,
        <emphasis role="bold">./mySavedArrays</emphasis>, and saves all of
        your arrays, using the OPAQUE format, into that
        folder:<programlisting>$ /opt/scidb/14.8/bin/scidb_backup.py -s opaque mySavedArrays</programlisting>For
        usage details of the backup script, see the SciDB Reference
        Manual.</para>

        <note>
          <para>If your existing installation is earlier than 14.8, do not use
          the OPAQUE format for this step. OPAQUE is guaranteed to work only
          between consecutive releases of SciDB.</para>
        </note>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Stop SciDB.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>If you want to use the SciDB configuration from your existing
        installation as the basis for the 14.12 configuration file, make a
        backup copy of it somewhere. By default, the file is in the following
        location:<screen>opt/scidb/<emphasis role="bold">scidbOldVersion</emphasis>/etc/config.ini</screen></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">OPTIONAL.</emphasis> You can run multiple
        versions of SciDB. <!--
For details, see <xref linkend="multipleSciDBs"/>.
--> However, if you need only the latest version of SciDB, you can remove the
        previous version. If you installed to the default location, run the
        following command to remove the old version:<programlisting>sudo rm -Rf /opt/scidb/<emphasis
              role="bold">scidbOldVersion</emphasis>/</programlisting></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Remove any older version of SciDB. For CentOS and RHEL, remove
        scidb.list.* and p4.list.* from /etc/yum.repos.d, then perform the
        following command. <programlisting>yum list | grep scidb |awk '{print $1}' | grep '[a-zA-Z]' | xargs sudo rpm -e</programlisting>
        For Ubuntu, remove scidb.list.* and p4.list.* from
        /etc/apt/sources.list.d, then perform the following
        command.<programlisting>dpkg --list | grep scidb |awk '{print $2}' | xargs sudo dpkg --purge </programlisting></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Upgrade. </emphasis>Perform the following
        steps to upgrade to version 14.12 of SciDB.<orderedlist
            numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
              <para>Set up your configuration file. If you are starting from
              the configuration file you saved in step 3, be sure to change
              all occurrences of <emphasis
              role="bold">scidbOldVersion</emphasis> to <emphasis
              role="bold">scidbNewVersion</emphasis>. After you edit the file,
              make a note of where you save it.</para>

              <para>Typically, the following settings are
              affected:<programlisting>install_root=/opt/scidb/14.8
pluginsdir=/opt/scidb/14.8/lib/scidb/plugins
logconf=/opt/scidb/14.8/share/scidb/log4cxx.properties</programlisting></para>

              <para>Also, be sure to add the following setting to the
              configuration file (if it does not already
              exist):<programlisting>enable-catalog-upgrade=true</programlisting>For
              more details about the configuration file, see <xref
              linkend="ConfiguringSciDB"/>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Run the cluster install procedure, available at 
<ulink
    url="www.scidb.org/forum/viewforum.php?f=16">www.scidb.org/forum/viewforum.php?f=16</ulink>.
              On the command line that invokes cluster install, include the
              configuration file (the one you saved in step 5a) as a
              parameter. See the cluster install README file for
              details.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Restart SciDB. Use the following command:</para>

              <programlisting>scidb.py initall <replaceable>scidb_cluster_name</replaceable></programlisting>

              <note>
                <para>If you get an error that says SciDB needs to upgrade the
                system catalog, and that the action failed, make sure to set
                the <code>enable-catalog-upgrade</code> parameter to <emphasis
                role="bold">true</emphasis>, as detailed in step <emphasis
                role="bold">6a</emphasis>.</para>
              </note>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Restore. </emphasis>After you have the new
        version of SciDB running, restore any data that you backed up in step
        1. For example, if you used the command in step 1 to backup your
        arrays, you would run the following command to restore
        them:<programlisting>$ /opt/scidb/14.12/bin/scidb_backup.py -r opaque mySavedArrays</programlisting></para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
</chapter>
