<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbookV4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id="insertOperator">
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>insert</refname>

    <refpurpose><indexterm>
        <primary>arrays</primary>

        <secondary>inserting data</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>data</primary>

        <secondary>inserting</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>insert</primary>

        <secondary>operator</secondary>
      </indexterm>Insert values from a source array into a target
    array.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <synopsis>insert(<replaceable>source_array</replaceable>,<replaceable>target_array</replaceable>);</synopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>The insert operator has two effects. One effect is to update the
    target array by inserting values from the source array. This means that
    the <literal>insert</literal> operator is a write operator, like the
    <literal>store()</literal> operator.</para>

    <para>The other effect is to produce a result array identical to the
    updated target array. This means that you can use the insert operator as
    an operand of other SciDB operators, although using the
    <literal>insert()</literal> operator inside any other write operator (such
    as <literal>store()</literal>) can yield unpredictable results.</para>

    <para>The source array and target array must be compatible. For the insert
    operator, compatible means the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The source and target arrays must have the same number of
        attributes.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Note: </emphasis>To the insert operator,
        attribute names are immaterial; the attribute names in the source and
        target arrays need not match. Rather, the first attribute of the
        source corresponds to the first attribute of the target; the second to
        the second, and so on.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the left-to-right ordering of attributes in each array, each
        pair of corresponding attributes must have the same datatype and the
        same null/not null setting.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The source and target arrays must have the same number of
        dimensions.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Note: </emphasis>Here too, the names are
        immaterial. Source dimensions and target dimensions correspond based
        on the left-to-right order of dimensions.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the left-to-right ordering of dimensions in each array, each
        pair of corresponding dimensions must have the same dimension starting
        index.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For each cell location of the target array, the insert operator
    writes values according to the following rules:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the corresponding cell location of the source array is empty,
        the insert operator does not write anything. At that cell location of
        the target array, an empty cell would remain empty, null values would
        remain null, and other values would remain unchanged.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If the corresponding cell location of the source array is
        non-empty, the insert operator changes the corresponding cell of the
        target array to match the value of the source. This has the following
        effects:<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Null values in the source can overwrite non-null values in
              the target.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If the cell location of the target array was initially
              empty, it will be non-empty after the insert operation.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>The AFL <code>insert()</code> operator provides the same
      functionality as the AQL <code><command>INSERT INTO</command></code>
      statement. The <literal>merge</literal> operator is also similar, except
      that <link linkend="mergeOperator">merge</link> is not a write operator
      (that is, merge does not store the result of the operation).</para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Limitations</title>

    <para>For each corresponding pair of dimensions in the source and
    target:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the target dimension is bounded, the source dimension must
          also be bounded and the respective upper bounds must be
          equal.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the target dimension is unbounded, the source dimension can
          be unbounded.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the target dimension is unbounded and the source dimension
          is bounded, the source dimension's chunk size must divide the source
          dimension's size evenly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <informalexample>
      <para>These examples show the behavior of the <code>insert()</code>
      operator.</para>
    </informalexample>

    <informalexample>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Show array A. Note that row 1 has only empty cells, row 2 has
          only null values, and row 3 has only non-null values.<para><programlisting>AFL% scan(A);
  </programlisting><screen>[
[(),(),()],
[(null),(null),(null)],
[('a7'),('a8'),('a9')]
]</screen></para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Show array B. Note that column 1 has only empty cells, column
          2 has only null values, and column 3 has only non-null
          values.<para><programlisting>AFL% scan(B);
  </programlisting><screen>[
[(),(null),('b3')],
[(),(null),('b6')],
[(),(null),('b9')]
]</screen></para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Insert values from A into B. <para><programlisting>AFL% insert(A,B)
  </programlisting><screen>[
[(),(null),('b3')],
[(null),(null),(null)],
[('a7'),('a8'),('a9')]
]</screen></para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><indexterm>
              <primary>array versions</primary>
            </indexterm>Show the versions of B. Version 1 is the original
          version of B. Version 2 is the version resulting from the insert
          operation of the previous step. <para><programlisting>AQL% <command>SELECT</command> * <command>FROM</command> versions(B)
  </programlisting><screen>{VersionNo} version_id,timestamp
{1} 1,'2014-04-10 17:39:39'
{2} 2,'2014-04-10 17:39:40'
</screen></para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Insert values from B (the original version of B—unchanged by
          the previous insert operation) into A.<para><programlisting>AFL% insert (B@1, A)
  </programlisting><screen>[
[(),(null),('b3')],
[(null),(null),('b6')],
[('a7'),(null),('b9')]
]</screen></para></para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </informalexample>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
