<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"docbookV4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry>
  <refnamediv id="redimension">
    <refname>redimension</refname>

    <refpurpose><indexterm>
        <primary>dimensions</primary>

        <secondary>adding</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>dimensions</primary>

        <secondary>redimensioning</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>redimension</primary>

        <secondary>operator</secondary>
      </indexterm>Produces a result array using some or all of the variables
    of a source array, potentially changing some or all of those variables
    from dimensions to attributes or vice versa, and optionally calculating
    aggregates to be included in the result array.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <synopsis>AFL% redimension(<replaceable>source_array</replaceable>,<replaceable>
                 template_array</replaceable>|<replaceable>schema_definition
                 </replaceable><optional>, <replaceable>aggregate_call_n </replaceable>(source_attribute) 
                            [as result_attribute]</optional>...)</synopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>The redimension operator produces a result array using data from a
    source array.</para>

    <para>When you use redimension, you must decide two things:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>How will the variables of the source array appear in the result
        array?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How will cell collisions be handled?</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For each variable of the source array, you have these choices for
    how to use it in the result array:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Include the variable without modification (i.e., an attribute
        remains an attribute and a dimension remains a dimension).</para>

        <para>To include an attribute without modification, simply include in
        the schema definition of the result array an attribute of the same
        data type with the same name. The analogous rule holds for including
        dimensions without modification.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Include the variable, but convert it (from an attribute to a
        dimension or vice versa)</para>

        <para>To convert an attribute to a dimension, simply include in the
        schema definition for the result array a dimension with the same name
        and datatype as the attribute from the source array. The analogous
        process holds for converting dimensions to attributes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Exclude the variable</para>

        <para>To exclude a variable, simply omit it from the schema definition
        of the result array. Even if you exclude a variable, its data can
        still contribute to the result array through aggregates.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Note that a single use of the redimension operator can make all of
    the above kinds of modifications to the various variables in the source
    array.</para>

    <para>Depending on how you arrange the source array's variables in the
    target array, the redimension operator might encounter cell collisions. A
    cell collision occurs when the redimension operator generates multiple
    candidate cell values for a single cell location of the target
    array.</para>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>collisions</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>cell collisions</primary>
      </indexterm>If the redimension operator produces a collision at a cell
    location, SciDB will produce a single cell from all of the candidate
    cells. The attributes of that cell in the target array will be populated
    as follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the target attribute was declared as the value of an
        aggregate function, the value will be the value of that function
        calculated over the set of candidate cells for that cell location. For
        each aggregate you calculate, a nullable attribute to accommodate it
        must exist in the target array's schema. The attribute must have the
        appropriate datatype for that aggregate function.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If the target attribute is simply the value of an attribute from
        the source array (rather than an aggregate function), the value of the
        target attribute will be from an arbitrarily chosen candidate cell for
        that location. If there are several such attributes in the target
        array, their values will all come from the same candidate cell.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The schema for the result array must accommodate the output of the
    redimension operator. Specifically:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If a variable in the source array appears in the result array,
        the two variables must match in name and data type.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If the redimension operator uses an aggregate, an attribute for
        that aggregate value must exist in the result array. The attribute
        must allow nulls and must be of the appropriate datatype for that
        aggregate function.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The result array cannot include any other variables besides
        variables that appear in the source array, and attributes to
        accommodate aggregate values.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Inputs</title>

    <para>The <literal>redimension</literal> operator takes the following
    arguments:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">source_array</emphasis>: a source array
          with one or more attributes and one or more dimensions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">template_array |
          schema_definition</emphasis>: an array or schema from which the
          output attributes and dimensions can be acquired. All the dimensions
          in the target must exist either in the source array attributes or
          dimensions, with one exception. One new, synthetic dimension is
          allowed. All the target attributes (other than those that are the
          results of aggregate calls) must exist either in the source array
          attributes or dimensions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis
          role="bold">aggregate_call</emphasis>_<replaceable>n</replaceable>:
          Zero or more aggregate calls.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Limitations</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Each attribute or dimension to be changed must be of type
        int64.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Except for newly added aggregate values, the variables in the
        new array must be a subset of the variables in the source
        array.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If a dimension of the new array corresponds to an attribute of
        the source array:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The dimension must be large enough to accommodate all
            distinct values of that attribute present in the source
            array.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The attribute in the source array can allow null values, but
            cells for which the attribute is null will not be included in the
            output.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you use aggregates as part of the redimension operator, the
        destination attributes—the attributes that will contain the aggregate
        values—must allow null values.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <informalexample>
      <para>This example redimensions a raw 1-dimensional array into a
      2-dimensional array by transforming two of the attributes into
      dimensions. This example uses the data set in the file raw.csv shown
      here: <programlisting language="test">--shell --command=cat $DOC_DATA/raw.csv
 --show-query=no
 --show-output=yes
</programlisting></para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Create an array named raw, to accommodate the data shown in
          the listing above. <programlisting language="test">--aql CREATE ARRAY raw 
      &lt;pos: int64, device: int64, val: float&gt; 
      [offset=0:*,5,0];
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=no </programlisting></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Convert the csv file to SciDB format. You will need to exit
          your iquery session or do this in a new terminal window because the
          csv2scidb tool is run at the command line.<programlisting
          language="test">--shell --command=csv2scidb -p NNN -s 1 
          &lt; $DOC_DATA/raw.csv &gt; 
            $DOC_DATA/raw.scidb
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=no</programlisting></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Load the data:<programlisting language="test">--aql LOAD raw FROM '../tests/harness/testcases/data/doc/raw.scidb';
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=yes
</programlisting></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Create an array with dimensions device and pos to be the
          redimension target:<programlisting language="test">--aql create array A
      &lt;val: float&gt;
      [device=1:5,5,0, pos=1:5,5,0];
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=no
</programlisting></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Redimension the source array raw into result array
          A:<programlisting language="test">--afl redimension(raw, A);
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=yes</programlisting></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Redimension the source array raw into result array A and store
          the result. Remember, the redimension operator produces a result
          array, but does not store the result.<programlisting
          language="test">--afl store(redimension(raw, A),A);
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=no</programlisting></para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </informalexample>

    <informalexample>
      <para>This example redimensions a 2-dimensional source array into a
      1-dimensional result array with aggregates. The result array has one
      cell for each row of the source array.</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Show the schema of the 2-dimensional source
          array:<programlisting language="test">--afl show(A);
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=yes</programlisting></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Show the contents of the 2-dimensional source
          array:<programlisting language="test">--afl scan(A);
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=yes
</programlisting></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Create an array for the 1-dimensional result; note that the
          attributes are declared to allow null values:<programlisting
          language="test">--aql create array Position 
         &lt;minVal:float null, 
          avgVal:double null, 
          maxVal:float null&gt; 
         [pos=1:5,5,0];
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=no
</programlisting></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Use the redimension operator to produce the 1-dimensional
          result array that includes aggregates:<programlisting
          language="test">--afl redimension(A,Position,
            min(val) as minVal, 
            avg(val) as avgVal, 
            max(val) as maxVal);
 --show-query=yes
 --show-output=yes
</programlisting></para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </informalexample>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
