<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"docbookV4.5/docbookx.dtd" >
  <section xml:id="DataModelInstall">
    <title>Visualizing a Completed SciDB Installation</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>architecture</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>SciDB</primary>

        <secondary>architecture</secondary>
      </indexterm>This section describes the pieces of a completed SciDB
    installation.</para>

    <section xml:id="DM_IC">
      <title>The SciDB Installation and Its Clusters</title>

      <para>The chapter describes the process for creating one SciDB
      Installation, which consists of one or more SciDB clusters. The
      following conceptual data model diagram expresses this
      graphically.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>SciDB Cluster</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="500" contentwidth="400"
                       depth="100"
                       fileref="../graphics/dm_InstallationHasClusters.png"
                       scale="30" valign="top" width="400"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The figure asserts the following: There are SciDB installations.
      Each SciDB installation has an arbitrary ID and SciDB clusters. There
      are SciDB clusters. Each SciDB cluster has a cluster name, a base path,
      and belongs to one SciDB installation. Within any SciDB installation,
      Each SciDB cluster name is unique.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The data models shown in this chapter are purely conceptual.
        They do not describe any physical data characteristics or connote any
        particular meta-model such as relational, object-oriented, etc. For a
        complete description of this notation, see Mastering Data Modeling: A
        User-Driver Approach by John Carlis et al. (Addison-Wesley,
        2001)</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="DM_CSI">
      <title>The SciDB Cluster, Servers, and Instances</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>cluster</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>SciDB</primary>

          <secondary>cluster</secondary>
        </indexterm>Each SciDB cluster consists of one or more servers, each
      of which can host one or more server instances.</para>

      <para>Like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>SciDB Servers and Instances</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="500" contentwidth="400"
                       depth="350"
                       fileref="../graphics/dm_clusterHasServerHasInstance.png"
                       scale="30" valign="top" width="400"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The figure asserts the following: There are SciDB installations.
      Each SciDB installation has an arbitrary ID and SciDB clusters. There
      are SciDB clusters. Each SciDB cluster has a cluster name, a base path,
      and belongs to one SciDB Installation. Within any SciDB installation,
      each SciDB cluster name is unique. There are servers. Each server has an
      IP address, belongs to one SciDB cluster, and can host multiple
      instances. There are instances. <indexterm class="startofrange"
          id="portnumbers">
          <primary>port numbers</primary>
        </indexterm>Each instance is hosted by one server. Each instance has a
      port number. Each instance has a unique combination of server and port
      number. (That is, two instances can have the same port number, but only
      if they are hosted by different servers.)</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="DM_CI_WI">
      <title>The Coordinator Instance and Worker Instances</title>

      <para>Every instance is either a coordinator instance, a worker
      instance, or both. Each SciDB cluster will have exactly one coordinator
      instance.</para>

      <para>Like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>SciDB Instances: Coordinator and Workers</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="500" contentwidth="400"
                       depth="400"
                       fileref="../graphics/dm_instanceBeCoordinatorOrWorker.png"
                       scale="30" valign="top" width="400"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <note>
        <para>A worker instance can also serve as the coordinator instance.
        Such an instance is typically referred to as the coordinator instance,
        but it can share in the workload of SciDB queries like any other
        worker instance.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The figure asserts the following: There are SciDB installations.
      Each SciDB installation has an arbitrary ID and SciDB clusters. There
      are SciDB clusters. Each SciDB cluster has a cluster name, a base path,
      and belongs to one SciDB installation. Within any SciDB installation,
      each SciDB cluster name is unique. There are servers. Each server has an
      IP address, belongs to one SciDB cluster, and can host multiple
      instances. There are instances. Each instance is hosted by one server.
      Each instance has a port number. Each instance has a unique combination
      of server and port number. (That is, two instances can have the same
      port number, but only if they are hosted by different servers.) An
      instance can be a coordinator instance, a worker instance, or both.
      Every coordinator instance is an instance. Every worker instance is an
      instance. Each coordinator instance coordinates the work of one SciDB
      cluster, and each SciDB cluster can be coordinated by one coordinator
      instance.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="DM_CS_WS">
      <title>The Coordinator Server and Worker Servers</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>coordinator server</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>instances</primary>

          <secondary>worker</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>worker server</primary>
        </indexterm>Whichever server hosts the coordinator instance is known
      as the coordinator server. The other servers as known as worker servers.
      In most contexts, the distinction between the coordinator server and
      worker servers is immaterial, and they are collectively known as
      servers. The installation instructions in this chapter direct you to
      install Postgres on the coordinator server. Although the coordinator
      server must host the coordinator instance, it can also host other
      (worker) instances.</para>

      <para>Like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>SciDB Servers: Coordinator and Workers</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="500" contentwidth="400"
                       depth="400"
                       fileref="../graphics/dm_serverBeCoordinatorOrWorker.png"
                       scale="30" valign="top" width="400"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The figure asserts the following: There are SciDB installations.
      Each SciDB installation has an arbitrary ID and SciDB clusters. There
      are SciDB clusters. Each SciDB cluster has a cluster name, a base path,
      and belongs to one SciDB installation. Within any SciDB installation,
      each SciDB cluster name is unique. There are servers. Each server has an
      IP address, belongs to one SciDB cluster, and can host multiple
      instances. There are instances. Each instance is hosted by one server.
      Each instance has a port number. Each instance has a unique combination
      of server and port number. (That is, two instances can have the same
      port number, but only if they are hosted by different servers.) An
      instance can be a coordinator instance, a worker instance, or both. Each
      coordinator instance coordinates the work of one SciDB cluster, and each
      SciDB cluster can be coordinated by one coordinator instance. A server
      can be a coordinator server or a worker server. The coordinator server
      hosts the coordinator instance (and because every coordinator instance
      is an instance, might also host other instances). The coordinator server
      will ultimately host the Postgres installation.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="DM_DP_D">
      <title>Disk Partitions and Directories</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>partitions</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>disk partitions</primary>
        </indexterm>When two or more instances are hosted by the same server,
      each of those instances requires its own directory to store SciDB
      database files. Those directories could be on the same disk
      partition.</para>

      <para>Like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Disk Partitions and Directories</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="500" contentwidth="400"
                       depth="350"
                       fileref="../graphics/dm_disksAndPartitions.png"
                       scale="30" valign="top" width="400"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The figure asserts the following: There are SciDB installations.
      Each SciDB installation has an arbitrary ID and SciDB clusters. There
      are SciDB clusters. Each SciDB cluster has a cluster name, a base path,
      and belongs to one SciDB installation. Within any SciDB installation,
      each SciDB cluster name is unique. There are servers. Each server has an
      IP address, belongs to one SciDB cluster, and can host multiple
      instances. There are instances. Each instance is hosted by one server.
      <indexterm class="endofrange" startref="portnumbers">
          <primary>port numbers</primary>
        </indexterm>Each instance has a port number. Each instance has a
      unique combination of server and port number. (That is, two instances
      can have the same port number, but only if they are hosted by different
      servers.) There are disk partitions. Each disk partition belongs to one
      server, and has a unique mount point and can have multiple directories.
      Each directory in on one disk partition, has a directory name, and can
      contain data for exactly one instance. Each instance stores its SciDB
      data on one directory.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="DM_Complete">
      <title>Complete SciDB Installation</title>

      <para>The complete data model described in the preceding sections is
      shown below. The model can help you visualize important distinctions
      that arise during the installation process. For example, some steps of
      the installation apply to all servers, whereas others apply only to the
      coordinator server. Likewise, some steps apply only to the coordinator
      instance, whereas other steps apply to all instances.</para>

      <para>The complete model is here:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>SciDB Installation</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="500" contentwidth="400"
                       depth="400" fileref="../graphics/dm_installFull.png"
                       scale="30" valign="top" width="400"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <?dbfo-need height="1.5in" ?>

      <note>
        <para>Remember, this is merely a conceptual model to help you
        understand the building blocks of the installation process. It is a
        conceptual model—not intended to connote any physical data layout or
        any particular meta-model such as relational or object-oriented. For
        that matter, it presents a somewhat simplified view of a SciDB
        configuration, which is all you need to begin the installation
        process.</para>
      </note>
  </section>
</section>
